João Moreira

Summary

Data scientist with a strong statistics background and experience in big data, machine learning, and data visualization. Strong critical thinker who always welcomes a challenge. Passionate about explaining data science to non-technical audiences.

Highly effective collaborator

Education

Ph.D. Chemical Engineering, Northwestern University
 Thesis: The Effect of Gender Diversity in Creative Teams
M.Sc. Physics, University of Lisbon, Portugal
 Thesis: Evolutionary Dynamics of Cooperation in Multiplayer Games
B.Sc. Physics, University of Lisbon, Portugal
 2006–2009

Skills

Machine Learning regression, classification, clustering, neural networks, data cleansing, feature engineering **Statistical Modeling** hypothesis testing, time-series analysis, cross-validation, regularization, bootstrapping, MapReduce

Programming Python (numpy, scipy, pandas, scikit-learn, matplotlib, requests), R, BASH, LaTeX

Tools Jupyter notebook, Sublime Text, Git, Mercurial, Excel

Databases MySQL, MongoDB

Web Design HTML, CSS, Javascript, D3.js

Experience

Data Scientist and Instructor

Northwestern University

Jan. 2012-Sep. 2017

- Used maximum likelihood estimation to parameterize the distribution of the impact of scientific publications (~1TB dataset).
- Constructed a Django web application with interactive D3.js visualizations to showcase my data-driven ranking of scientific research: http://forecite.us.
- Demonstrated the existence of historical gender discrimination in the movie industry by performing time-series analysis on IMDb metadata of +15k movies.
- Created and delivered original course materials on web-scraping and object-oriented programming to over 100 students in 2 sessions of a 1-week long Python programming bootcamp.
- Organized and led discussion groups, and graded homeworks for all students in 4 undergraduate courses.
- Mentored 2 younger graduate students and 2 high-school interns on the principles of scientific research and basics of programming.

Data Science Intern

GadflyZone

Apr. 2016-Sep. 2016

- Constructed MySQL database of patents on Amazon Database Relational Services built from publicly available patent information.
- Used natural language processing and citation analysis to design a multidimensional scoring engine to predict a company's innovativeness.

Software Engineer

Narrative Science

Jun. 2014-Sep. 2014

• Developed system to automatically analyze performance of the company's artificial intelligence platform.